These two soldiers are on an important
mission.
Above them, the roar of the plane fades.
Below them lies their homeland, occupied
by the Nazis. And somewhere down there
is their target. Reinhard Hydrickch, the
butcher of Prague,
one of the key architects of the
Holocaust. Hitler calls him the man with
the iron heart. He's responsible for
more than a million and a half deaths
and he doesn't have the faintest idea
they're coming for him.
>> Confirmed.
>> Warning. This video includes
descriptions of suicide and mass murder
committed under the Nazi regime. Our
coverage is largely based on these two
books.
This is a photo of Reinhard Hydrich and
his wife Lena. It was taken in May 1942
at the Volenstein Pal in Prague where
they attended a concert. Reinhard
Hydrich loves music. He's the son of a
singer and composer. But despite showing
musical talent as a child, he chose a
very different path for himself. After
graduating from school, he joined the
Reichkes Marina, the German Navy.
Hydrickch is tall, blonde, and athletic.
He looks like he walked straight out of
a Nazi propaganda poster. But this
picture perfect facade is deceptive.
He speaks with a strangely thin,
high-pitched voice. He's said to have
been haunted by deep insecurity and
self-hatred. In school and also in the
Navy, people mock him. Rumors spread
that he has Jewish roots. They call him
Blonde Moses. in a Germany turning
toward Nazism. It's a nickname he
despises.
In December 1930, he meets Lena von Oen
at a dance in Keel. After just four
dates, they get engaged. It's said that
he was drawn to her Nordic looks, maybe
hoping they'd silence those rumors about
him having Jewish ancestry.
But then, scandal strikes the newly
engaged couple. Hydrickch is brought
before a naval court of honor. A former
girlfriend accuses him of breaking a
promise to marry her. He's discharged
from the Navy, a humiliating fall from
grace. But unfortunately, it's not the
end of his career.
A few months later, a family friend
introduces him to Heinrich Himmler.
Heddrich joins the Nazi party and the
SS.
And from there, his rise is meteoric.
In just a few years, Hydrickch becomes
one of the most powerful men in Nazi
Germany. He's made chief of the Reich
Security main office, the SS and police
agency.
In 1938, he orchestrates Crystal
Knocked, the night of broken glass.
Across Germany, synagogues burn, Jewish
businesses are ransacked, and thousands
of people are arrested, beaten, or
killed.
In July 1941, Hydrickch is tasked with
planning what the Nazis call the final
solution to the Jewish question, the
blueprint for the systematic mass murder
of Europe's Jews. Hydrich is the boss of
Adolf Ikeman, another key Holocaust
architect we covered in this video.
A few months later, in autumn 1941,
Hydrickch receives a significant
promotion. He's sent to Prague as deputy
Reich protector of Bohemia and Moravia.
Nazi Germany occupied the Czech lands in
1939 and the Reich protector Constantine
Vonroth governs the territory. But Von
Neurroth is considered too lax. So
Hydrickch becomes the de facto governor.
He definitely isn't too lax. Hitler has
sent the man with the iron heart.
Hydrickch orders mass arrests,
executions, and deportations.
Thousands of checks are sent to
concentration camps. His reign of terror
earns him a title that history will
never forget. The butcher of Prague. To
the outside world, it appears Hydrickch
has crushed the Czech resistance. But in
the shadows, a plan to assassinate him
is in motion.
While Hydrickch makes himself
comfortable with his family in his
castle near Prague, hundreds of
kilometers away, two soldiers are
training to kill him. The Czech
government is in exile. Its leaders are
in London. Czech military intelligence
is cooperating with the British special
operations executive. Together, they
plan a top secret mission to assassinate
Hydrickch.
Operation Anthropoid.
Enter Yan Kubish and Ysef Gabchuk.
Meeting in Poland in 1939, they
eventually join the French Foreign
Legion, the only way to fight back. In
the ranks of the Legion, they become
good friends. After the fall of France,
Czech forces are moved to Britain. In
the autumn of 1941, Gabchuk is chosen
for Operation Anthropoid. When his
partner suffers an injury during
training, Gabchuk insists that Kubish be
the one to replace him. Both men are
proud soldiers who had watched their
homeland fall to the Nazis without a
fight. Now they're determined to strike
back, no matter what the cost. Together,
they prepare for one of the most
dangerous missions of the war,
to strike at the heart of the Nazi
regime. 3D scenes like these are made by
humans. Greetings from our team. But to
keep things running behind the scenes,
we rely on partners like our long-term
sponsor, Udu. UDO is an all-in-one
business management software. It's
designed to cover everything you need to
run and grow a company with more than 45
applications, including a powerful
project management app. It lets you
create projects with custom stages, add
tasks, and assign a person in charge.
You can set up each task with
priorities, tags, and deadlines to keep
things clear. Collaborate easily with
your team and stay productive wherever
you are. The app allows you to monitor
your project through different views
from conbon to Gant and list view. The
first UDO app is free for life,
including unlimited hosting and support.
When your business grows, Udu grows with
you. All apps work seamlessly together
and are available from $19.90 per month.
Scan this QR code or check the link in
the description to get started.
In the early hours of December 29, 1941,
a British Halifax bomber drops its
deadly cargo, Gabchic and Kubish. But
heavy snow blinds the crew, making
navigation nearly impossible. So they
accidentally drop Gabchic and Kubish at
the wrong location.
Instead of landing east of Pilson, they
end up east of Prague. As they approach
the ground, Gabchek misjudges the height
and injures his left foot. Now they have
no idea where they are. It's night and
it's cold.
The two soldiers bury their parachutes
in the snow and take shelter in the
abandoned tunnels of an old stone
quarry. Their landing hasn't gone
unnoticed. During the night, a local
gamekeeper heard the plane, climbed onto
the roof of his house, and saw two
parachutes heading toward him. The next
morning, he finds the buried parachutes
and follows a trail of footprints in the
snow. It doesn't take him long to find
Gabchick and Kubish and confront them.
The young men pretend to be surveyors,
but their cover story quickly falls
apart, and they reluctantly admit the
truth. Luckily, the gamekeeper wants to
help them. They're stunned to find out
they've landed 20 m from Prague, far
from their contacts. Cabshik is injured
and the mission already looks doomed.
But then fate intervenes. A local miller
who also heard the plane that night
tracks them down. He's a member of Soal,
a banned Czech nationalist group and
offers to connect them with the
underground network in Prague. It
violates the strictest rules of their
mission. No contact with the local
resistance until their mission is over.
But they're desperate. They have no
choice but to accept help. Over the next
few months, they're sheltered by a
network of brave families, ordinary
people risking everything to feed and
hide them.
Reinhard Hydrickch is busy organizing
the infamous Vonz Conference, a meeting
called to streamline the mass murder of
Jews.
He doesn't realize that all the while
two men are observing him, learning his
habits, noting every route and ritual.
They even have inside help from people
working in his castle. They sketch out
several ideas for how to take him out.
An attack at his castle or his estate
isn't an option. The SS guards them too
closely. But they see another opening.
Hydrickch always travels without guards,
accompanied only by his chauffeur. It's
the one time he's exposed. So, they
decide to strike while he's on the road.
They consider stretching a wire across
the street to force his car to slow
down, but time is running out. They hear
rumors that Hydrickch might leave Prague
soon. The pressure mounts and they need
to move quickly.
May 26, 1942.
In a magnificent concert hall, Hydrickch
and his wife enjoy compositions by his
father, Bruno. Not far away, two men
finish their final checks. Tomorrow,
they'll attempt to kill the butcher of
Prague. Gabchic is armed with a British
Sten gun. Kubish holds the explosives.
They pack two briefcases. One contains
the disassembled Sten gun, while the
other holds two bombs. To an observer,
the briefcases look ordinary. The
weapons are hidden beneath layers of
fresh grass. It's the perfect cover.
With wartime food shortages, many locals
keep rabbits, so carrying grass for feed
is a common sight.
The next morning, Reinhard Hydrick's day
begins peacefully. It's a fresh spring
morning. He finishes breakfast and plays
with his three children. His wife is
pregnant with a fourth. At around 10:00,
he leaves the safety of his castle with
his chauffeur.
On a narrow street in the Leebane
district on the outskirts of Prague,
Kabic waits. Kubish is positioned here
just a few meters away. Both have stood
here for over an hour, tense, silent,
ready. Then finally, Hydrick's
Mercedes-Benz pulls up. Not yet.
Not yet.
Now Gabchic steps forward, throws off
his raincoat, raises the sten, and pulls
the trigger,
but nothing happens. Months of training
for this one moment, and the gun jams.
Maybe grass clogged the mechanism. The
Sten had a reputation for jamming
easily. Or maybe it's just bad luck.
We'll never know. Idrich thinks there's
only one attacker, so he yells at his
driver to stop and draws his pistol.
Kubish ceizes the moment,
but he misjudges his throw.
Hydrich survives. Kubish scramles onto
his bicycle and disappears down the
street. Gabic is chased by Hydrickch's
driver and flees into a nearby butcher
shop. When the driver bursts in, Gabchic
finally makes the stem work, shooting
him in the leg and escaping.
Both assassins get away, but there's no
sense of triumph. The mission failed.
They haven't eliminated their target.
But Hydrickch is critically wounded by
the explosion. He's rushed to Balobsa
Hospital in a passing delivery truck.
And on June 4, 1942, 8 days after the
attack, Reinhardt Hydrickch subsumes to
his wounds.
Immediately after the assassination, the
Gestapo launches a massive manhunt for
the attackers, but they have no real
leads. Frustrated, the regime demands
blood to avenge the death of the deputy
right protector. The Nazis choose the
village of Leita, which has 503
residents, for their revenge. They
suspect some within the village support
the attackers, but there's no real
evidence of this.
On June 10, 1942, a few hours after
midnight, Nazi troops raid the village.
They shoot 173 men on the spot. The
women are sent to Ravensbrook
concentration camp. Children under a
year old and those selected for
re-education through placement in German
families remain alive. All other
children are killed at the Chelno
extermination camp in Poland. Of the
village's former 503 inhabitants, only
143 women and 17 children survived the
war. After murdering or deporting the
villagers, the Nazis destroy the entire
village, the homes, the church, even the
cemetery. They film the entire process.
By 1943,
only this empty field remains. For the
Nazis, the destruction of the town is
symbolic of their power. Usually, they
would try to hide their war crimes, but
this time, their brutality is on full
display. The bloodbath turned into
propaganda.
Fore.
But even after burning Leita to the
ground and murdering most of its
inhabitants, the Nazis aren't done. They
want to find the men behind the attack.
So they announce an amnesty. Anyone who
comes forward with information will be
spared. And there's a reward. A million
Reichkes marks. One of Gabchic and
Kubish's comrades takes the deal. His
name is Carl Chugda. His story is
similar to theirs. He fled to Poland,
joined the French Foreign Legion, and
trained in Britain for special
operations.
He was also brought to the Protectorate
for a mission. But on June 16, 1942, he
decides to collaborate with the Gestapo
in Prague. In exchange for a new
identity and the cash, he gives them the
assassins and the names of the families
sheltering them. One of them is the
Moraveets family. The Gestapo storms
their home. The mother takes her own
life with poison, but her son is taken
for interrogation. Using truly
unspeakable methods, they break him. He
eventually tells them what his mother
once told him. If you're ever in serious
trouble, go to the church of St. Siril
and Methodius.
Inside this Orthodox church, Gabchic and
Kubish have found refuge. Here, in the
damp darkness of the crypt, the two
assassins and five other paratroopers
wait for orders from London. They know
about Leita. They know that hundreds of
innocents have already died in the Nazi
reprisals. Crushed by guilt, they
consider committing suicide in a public
park. They hope that leaving a note
claiming responsibility might finally
stop the killings.
But before they can make their move,
it's too late. The Nazis surround the
church. Then all hell breaks loose.
Seven men against more than 700 SS and
Gustapo troops. When the Nazis can't
break through their defenses, they flood
the crypt. Kubish dies from injuries he
suffered in the firefight. Then one by
one, the other paratroopers choose death
over capture. Some use cyanide, others
their last bullets. In the end, both of
Hdrich's assassins are dead. Dozens of
resistors, entire families are executed
for helping them. Among them, Bishop
Gast and other members of the Czech
Orthodox Church. And the Nazis revenge
doesn't end there. Just days later, they
wipe another village, the Jaci, off the
map. Every adult in the village is
executed. Most children are deported and
killed, and the village is burned to the
ground. Like Leita, the Jaci simply
ceases to exist.
After the end of World War II, Nazi
official Carl Herman Frank, who ordered
the mass murder in Leisa and Ljaki, was
convicted and executed.
Carell Chugda had continued to work with
the Gestapo until the end of the war. He
then attempted to flee but was captured
and sentenced to death. He was executed
in Prague on April 29, 1947.
Even after her husband's death, Lena
Hydrickch remained a prominent figure.
She didn't return to Germany until 1945.
After the country's surrender, her
husband's property was seized,
confiscated as the assets of a war
criminal. She spent the rest of her life
defending his legacy, repeatedly denying
that her late husband was responsible
for any war crimes. In the 1950s, she
won several lawsuits against West
Germany, securing a substantial widow's
pension and regaining her luxurious
summer home.
Today, a memorial stands at the site of
the ambush in Prague. It honors Ysef
Gabbik, Yan Kubish, and a third figure
representing the Czech civilian
resistance.
In the Czech villages of Leita and
Ljaki, memorials mark the sights of the
mass killings. These places serve as not
just reminders of lives lost, but as
warnings to never let something like
this happen ever again.